hey everyone it's melanie ham welcome
back to my channel today's video we're
gonna make this
washcloth i made this just for myself
and i was showing it on my instagram and
i got so many messages asking for the
tutorial so i'm gonna do that today so
this is a different yarn but i used 100
cotton here are some other cotton
options debbie bliss makes some really
nice ones ice yarns
a lion brand
another w blisters great ones out there
pick whichever one you want i asked in a
poll on my instagram you can follow me
on instagram if you want you can i'll
put it up right here um
i also don't pull if i should use a blue
or pink because i have several of these
skeins
and everyone's saying blue so far so
we're going to go with that so grab
your yarn
and grab your hook i love the clover
amore hooks they are my absolute
favorite but these are a total game
changer they're super lightweight i can
crochet a lot longer not sure what i was
waiting for why i didn't get them sooner
grab your yarn
and
if you're new to crocheting this is a
great beginner project a lot of times
you pull your yarn out from the center
and sometimes you pull out a big ball of
a mess
and sometimes you get lucky
all right so what we're going to do is
chain
you know
there's not a specific number of chains
you have to do in order to create this
pattern so if you want to make a little
guy or a big one or even more of a like
a wash rag dish rag for the kitchen and
you want it to even be bigger totally
cool this guy measures about nine inches
across
so i'm just going to make this one and
compare it
all right so we're going to start with a
slip knot
pull
insert your hook into that loop
and pull it down to tighten it
and then we're going to make our
foundation chain let your hook do the
work for you okay so try not to make it
too floppy but also try not to make it
too tight
i know that doesn't make a whole lot of
sense when you're a beginner but
if you
mess up on the foundation chain the good
thing with the washcloth is you can fix
it really easily and go back
i love making washcloths and recommend
them for beginners all the time because
you really can practice your stitching
and still be able to make something
practical even if it's not perfect
okay so you're going to yarn over
pull through
yarn over
yarn over pull through
kind of forms a braid of sorts yarn over
and you're going to do this until you
reach your desired
length
so for me it'll be about 9 inches and
again for this pattern the number the
multiple does not matter
if you are going to err on either side
of being looser or tighter error on the
side of being looser for that foundation
chain
all right so continue making your
foundation chain the length that you
would like so there's my foundation
chain
i did not count how many i did okay now
we're going to start with a double
crochet so that means we are going to
insert our hook in the third chain so
one so the one on the hook does not
count
one two
three
all right so we're going to yarn over
insert your hook
i like to go underneath two strands
from that foundation chain
yarn over pull through
three loops on your hook
yarn over
two loops
all right so that we've got our double
crochet now we're going to do a single
crochet
in that next stitch over
or the next chain the foundation chain
over i should say
insert your hook
yarn over pull through
yarn over
pull through both loops
there's your single crochet now we're
gonna go back to the double crochet
yarn over
insert it into the next chain
yarn over pull through
yarn over
pull through two
and two double crochet and then again
with our single crochet and that is
going to be
what you do
for the stitch
so we're going to alternate
so continue this all the way down
single double single double single
double
all the way till you get to the end i'll
meet you there
okay now we're almost done with the
first
row and it might look a little funny
it's not going to look
like
the stitch works up you know after
you've done several rows okay so you're
like wait does this look right
yes you're doing it right sometimes it
doesn't look like much at the start but
keep going okay
so
mine is i have a double
and then i have two left which means
it's going to be a single and then a
double i'm going to end on a double if
you end on a single totally cool i'll
tell you how to d to change it up okay
double in that last
or the first chain i should say
all right so now for me i did it i ended
on a double so i'm going to chain one
i'm going to turn my work
and i'm going to put a single crochet
in the top of that double
which is here
so right in the top of that double
crochet let's get a little closer
the top of the double crochet i'm going
to do a single crochet
okay and then the next stitch over is a
single crochet so that needs to be a
double crochet so you need to do the
alternate stitch on top of the previous
stitch
so this stitch i ended on a double so on
top of that needs to be a single crochet
okay so the next stitch should be a
single crochet that means on top of that
i need to do a double crochet
here
all right so that means if you ended on
a single crochet on that last or on the
first
the end of your first row you would
chain two and then put a double crochet
right in the top of that single crochet
okay that's all there is to it so if if
yours is a little bit different than
mine no big deal you're just going to
chain two and put the single the double
crochet there instead and that's all
there is to it so you're gonna
then continue doing the single double
single double
all the way across
if you ever lose track you just look at
that previous stitch
and
there's our single crochet and the
double crochet is going to kind of pop
out a little bit
because it's a little bit of a taller
stitch
but that's what's going to create that
really nice texture
okay so continue going down the second
row and i'll meet you at the end
to show you how to do the end
okay so in
here we go getting close to the end
we just did a double crochet so now we
need to do
a single crochet
okay and that's going to finish out our
end now that turning chain that we did
initially is not going to count as a
stitch
all right so we ended on a single here
so we're going to chain two
one
two we're gonna turn our work and a lot
of times when you start stitching with a
double crochet then you this counts as a
double crochet and then you actually
start your double crochet in the next
stitch over i'm not doing that on this
because i don't want there to be a
little hole
that's what can happen there can be kind
of like a little gap there and this just
helps keep your edges a little bit
straighter so what we're going to do
is
yarn over
and place a double crochet right in the
top of that stitch
it keeps our alternating
working out too so we did the double
crochet there on top of that previous
single crochet
here is the double crochet which needs a
on top of it
you can kind of see how that texture is
forming you're going to continue doing
that until you reach the desired size of
your washcloth now i don't know if this
is called a specific stitch
i just call it the single double because
and i love that it's really easy it's
really great for beginners
but as you know i love making things
that are really simple but that have a
special touch to it because you use the
special yarn or it looks more
complicated than it actually is all this
is
is a double crochet with a single
crochet and then you keep going continue
on with your washcloth i will finish
mine up i'll meet you back here and i'll
show you real quick how to fasten off
and weave in your tails in case you are
a beginner
but there you go happy stitching work on
your washcloth
alright everyone so here's my washcloth
it's all finished
take a look pretty nice huh okay so when
you're done with your row
i'll show you what to do to finish off
you need a yarn needle they have plastic
ones and they have metal ones
cut your yarn and leave a bit of a tail
so that we can weave in the end
and what we'll do just
if your hook is in that loop
pull it through
and then tighten that down so we've got
our yarn needle and we've got two ends
so what you'll do
is thread your needle
and then basically you want to weave in
the tails so that
they are secure and when you wash these
because you're going to wash them a
bunch of times because we want to use
these and love these
then they'll stay secure so what i like
to do is kind of go one direction
weaving it in
and then i will go back the other
direction
that way
if it does start to unravel
or does start to come out it's not going
to actually unravel or do anything it's
just
keeping that
secure
and you can even go all the way down
bring it back do it as many times as you
want until you
feel confident that it is secure
all right so once you feel good about it
trim it
there we go do your other one and you
are all set ready to go wash these with
your other towels you don't need to
treat it special or anything
now you've got your very own hand made
hand crocheted
cotton washcloth